Women's School of Planning and Architecture Records, 1974-1992
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Women's School of Planning and Architecture records
1974 - 1992
1974-81
Women's School of Planning and Architecture
MS 306
18 boxes (12.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Educational program and feminist collective. The Women's School of Planning and Architecture Records provides a detailed account of the successes and struggles of an experimental, non-hierarchical educational institution founded at the height of the 1970s women's movement. Records document the School's sessions on feminist architectural planning and design. There is also rich documentation of the founding, planning, and operation of the School. Materials include correspondence; histories; photographs; extensive audio-visual material; publications; publicity and memorabilia.
The Women's School of Planning and Architecture (WSPA) was an experiment in feminist education for women interested in architecture, planning, and environmental design. The School was founded by Katrin Adam, Ellen Perry Berkeley, Noel Phyllis Birkby (see also N. Phyllis Birkby Papers, Bobbie Sue Hood, Marie I. Kennedy, Joan Forrester Sprague, and Leslie Kanes Weisman. The founders had met as a result of the formation of professional organizations for women architects and planners (beginning in 1972) and through attendance at the first U.S. conferences on women in architecture in 1974 and 1975. These opportunities to meet and share experiences with other women professionals led them to a conviction that an alternative educational experience would be a valuable way to address the "shared common goals and interests not being met within the existing professional contexts" according to the 1975 WSPA brochure.
The same brochure describes the founders goals:
...to create a personally supportive atmosphere and a stimulating exchange of ideas in a vacation setting. We hope to encourage both personal and professional growth through a fuller integration of our values and identities as women with our values and identities as designers. Our aim is to create a forum within which we may discover and define the particular qualities, concerns, and abilities that we as women bring to the environmental design professions.
WSPA was deliberately experimental. It was to be a new form of organization providing a new style of educational experience. The Coordinators used feedback from participants to make adjustments and innovations designed to help the organization better meet its goals. WSPA's founders understood that the development of an effective alternative school meant that there would be no set format for WSPA sessions. Within a general set of criteria, they envisioned an ever-changing and evolving entity responsive to the needs of the participants.
The School aimed to attract participants from diverse backgrounds and geographic locations by making an interest in environmental design the only admission "requirement" and by holding each session at a different location. Tuition was kept to a minimum and work-study scholarships were available. While the focus of the earlier sessions could be characterized as "consciousness raising, skill building, and [theoretical discussion]" among women who were primarily professionals and academics, in its latter years WSPA was moving toward involvement in political activism based on collaboration with "grassroots women."
According to co-founders Noel Phyllis Birkby and Leslie Kanes Weisman, all participants in WSPA were considered members of a peer group "equally responsible and equally capable of making a contribution" (in "The Women's School of Planning and Architecture," in Learning Our Way: Essays in Feminist Education). Sessions were planned by a group of Coordinators who were essentially self-selected, based on their willinginess and ability to devote the time and energy necessary to bring off a successful session. This was not a volunteer commitment, but a professional engagement paid through income generated by tuition fees.
The curriculum was designed to offer subject matter unavailable in standard academic or professional settings. Courses were conducted by methods designed to "eliminate some of the effects of male-defined and identified educations." Instructors emphasized "the active participation of all members of the group, minimizing the role of the coordinators as experts or authorities," while maximizing their "roles as information sources and organizers" (Birkby and Weisman).
There were five WSPA sessions in all: at St. Joseph's College in Biddeford, Maine, in 1975; at Stephenson College in Santa Cruz, California, in 1976; at Roger Williams College in Bristol, Rhode Island, in 1978; at Regis College in Denver, Colorado, in 1979; and a weekend symposium in Washington, DC, in 1981. A session planned and advertised for 1980 at Hood College in Frederick, Maryland, was cancelled when registration targets were not met.
The level of energy and commitment required to create a new style of organization offering an ever-changing educational experience soon proved difficult to sustain. Adding to the complexity was the fact that Coordinators were scattered around the country, making communication and consensus-building extraordinarily difficult. Though WSPA remained a legal corporation after the final session in 1981, no additional sessions came to fruition. Internal struggles developed, the School was perpetually short of money, and, probably most importantly, no group of Coordinators came forward to take on the challenge of planning a session. In a 1989 piece on WSPA for the book Architecture: A Place for Women, Leslie Kanes Weisman described it as a product of its time, ideal for "the consciousness-raising task of defining problems," but less useful for "designing and implementing solutions."
The Women's School of Planning and Architecture Records consist of 10.5 linear feet of audiotapes, correspondence, memorabilia, memoranda, minutes, films, photographs, publications, slides, videotapes, and other materials. They date from 1974 to 1992 with the bulk of the materials documenting the period between 1974 and 1981. The Records contain rich documentation of the founding, planning, and operation of the School. They provide a detailed account of the successes and struggles of an experimental, non-hierarchical educational institution founded at the height of the 1970s women's movement.
The intentions of the School's founders are well documented in the publications and publicity materials in Series I as well as the Coordinators' Records (Series II). Because the Coordinators were scattered geographically and thus forced to communicate primarily by mail, the written record of their work is exceptionally rich. True to the experimental and unconventional nature of the organization, information in Series II is rarely in standardized formal documents such as minutes and reports. Formal minutes exist for a relatively brief period, but other kinds of records of the work of the group, such as notes and circular letters, abound.
Nearly two-thirds of the total volume of the surviving records is materials created for or during the sessions themselves. Sensitive to the ground breaking nature of their endeavor, the Coordinators arranged for extensive written and audio visual documentation of the first WSPA session in 1975, when large portions of the session were captured on video and audiotape (available in Series III and Series IV). Included in the Records is a finished film about the 1975 session. Documentation of sessions after 1975 is less comprehensive.
Related materials in the Sophia Smith Collection can be found in the personal papers of WSPA co-founder Noel Phyllis Birkby.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. General and Historical Material
II. Coordinators' Records
III. Sessions
IV. Audio Visual Material
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
The records of the Women's School of Planning and Architecture were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by the executors of the estate of founding coordinator Noel Phyllis Birkby in 1994 and by founding coordinator Ellen Perry Berkeley in 1997.
Search Terms
Architecture--Study and teaching--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women architects--United States--History--Sources; Women artists--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Architecture and women--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women's School of Planning and Architecture--History--Sources; Feminism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Lesbianism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Birkby, Phyllis; Berkeley, Ellen Perry; Vogel, Mary; Weisman, Leslie Kanes
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material can be found in the Phyllis Birkby Papers, Sophia Smith Collection.
Appendix: Descriptions by Barbara Hammer of WSPA films.
#1. WSPA, documentary, edited, approx. 30 min. 1976 Print- Original is reel #3 & #4. Lorna McNeur's name is on leader (?)
Shots of barns, houses, poster The Women's School of Planning & Architecture", 1976. Large number of women( probably the students and teachers) sitting on outdoor stairway, pan down to front steps, women all the way. Indoor shots of students in workshop. Scrapbook of black and white snaps shots of arch. patterns. Modules, pitched roofs, porches, etc. Diagrams and snaps probably used in workshop. Women making drawings. Women walking down path. Standing at seashore, exploring. Talking. Walking through reeds. Patting sand and building sand forms. Students making presentations. Phyllis' printing of description of days activities. Shots of video of women entering revolving glass doors/children in pushcarts. Class discussing situation. Children. At beach. (stopped watching here/second film break).
#2. CAKE CAMPUS. Color Sup. 8 film, will correspond to video tape.
WSPA. Interior shots of workshop, complete w/writing on wall. Women w/video cameras. Women in groups. Flying Saucer School - fantasy architectural school, could make spaces, women spaces, Flying Saucer - a plus for motion sickness. Someone drawing on someone's back. Writing on the wall - Vegetables Running Up Our Ears. Stuff like sauna and swimming pool. Sign - Be Able To Eat Our Own Forms. Mosquito Eaters, Mechanics, Plumbers. Film looks in good shape. Hardly any scratches. Women are building models, looks like a flying saucer model made out of cake, cutting forms. Decorating w/marshmallos and all kinds of sugar. Looks like they are building architectural models of gumdrops, cookies, cake, unfortunately, soft focus on a lot of closeups, but long shots are good.
#3. WSPA (CONDENSED) Reel #1, Edited, Approx 24 min.
Lorna McNeur's name on leader; seems to be the maker. original (I think is same as print # 1)
#4. WSPA (CONDENSED) Reel #2, Approx. 15 min. Lorna McNeur. Edited. original
#5. MIME, Original, Super 8, 2 min. 1976
Two women mirror mime; WSPA slides filmed.
#6. WSPA 2 Sup. 8, 3 min. Group shots; a little dark.
- SERIES I. GENERAL AND HISTORICAL MATERIALS 1975-2002, undated
  - "Herstory" 1976-79 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-laws, incorporation papers, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial, 1976-79, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Library/Bibliographies, 1975-79, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Logo, graphics, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia, 1975-76, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Participant and mailing lists, 1975-79, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publications
    - Brochures, application forms, 1975-80 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Newsletter, 1975-80, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publicity, press releases, clippings, 1975-84, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Publicity mailing lists, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Reunion program, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Statement of goals, policies, purpose, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. COORDINATORS' RECORDS 1974-92, undated
  - Minutes, Oct 1975-Mar 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Coordinator correspondence, memoranda, notes
    - 1974-15 Mar 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4-12)
    - 16 Mar 1976-May 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1-14)
    - Jun 1977-Nov 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1-15)
    - Dec 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Symposium "Community Based Alternatives and Women in the '80s": correspondence, memoranda, minutes, 1980-81 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - Jul 1981-83, 1992, undated (Box 5, Folder 7-10)
  - General correspondence, 1975-79 (Box 5, Folder 11-16)
  - General correspondence, 1980-82 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Symposium "Community Based Alternatives and Women in the '80s": conference packet, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- SERIES III. SESSIONS 1975-82
  - First Session (1975), St. Francis College, Biddeford, ME, 10-23 Aug
    - Bibliography (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Collective Journal (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Core Courses [#3 cancelled]
      - #1 "The Community Context of Town Development" Ellen Perry Berkeley (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - #2 "Demystification of Tools in Relation to Design" Katrin Adam (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - #4 "Professionalism Redefined" Marie I. Kennedy and Joan Forrester Sprague (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - #5 "Urban Design: The Outside of Inside" Bobbie Sue Hood (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - #6 "Women and the Built Environment: Personal, Social, and Professional Perceptions" Noel Phyllis Birkby and Leslie Kanes Weisman (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence with participants, A - Z (Box 6, Folder 12-15)
    - Documentation (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Final Feedback Session (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - "Getting Acquainted" information forms (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Housing (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Memorabilia (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Notes, miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Part-time resource people (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Publicity (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Registration cards (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Testimony from participants (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Work study scholarships (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Second Session (1976), Stevenson College, Santa Cruz, CA, 8-22 Aug
    - Applications (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Bibliographies (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Core course: "The Writing Process: A Designer's Approach" (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Evaluation of session by coordinators (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Financial (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Location (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Memorabilia (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Planning questionnaire (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Publicity (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Registration cards (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Third Session (1978), Roger Williams College, Bristol, RI, 13-26 Aug
    - Applications (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Bibliography, reading list (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Coordinator credentials (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with participants, A-Z (Box 8, Folder 8-10)
    - Financial (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Memorabilia (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Packet for participants (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Participant information questionnaire, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Planning for future of WSPA (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Publicity (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Registration cards (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Schedule (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Work study (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Workshops
      - "Design for Non-traditional Living" (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - "Ecology of Sex Roles" (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Weekend (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Fourth Session (1979), Regis College, Denver, CO, 9-23 Aug
    - Applications, two-week session, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Applications, weekend session, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Bibliography (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Core courses, 1978-79 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Financial aid, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Information on resource women (faculty), 1979 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Participant list (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - schedule (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Proposed international session (1982): correspondence, notes, 1979-82, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
- SERIES IV. AUDIO-VISUAL MATERIAL 1975-79, undated
  - Audiotapes: Reel-to-Reel
    - "WSPA Narrative"1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "Master tapes"1975 (5 reels) (Box 10, Folder 2-6)
    - "WSPA stuff"1975 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - "WSPA Sound Tape"undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Audiotapes: Cassettes
    - First Session (1975), St. Francis College, Biddeford, ME
      - Discussion (coordinators doing planning?), 1975? (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Orientation, 10 Aug (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Core course #1: The Community Context of Town Development, Ellen Perry Berkeley, [Digital file available] (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Core course #1: Judy Potter (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
      - Core course #1: Cheri Chaney, planning (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
      - Core course #2: Demystification of Tools, Katrin Adam, [Digital file available] (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
      - Interview: Katrin Adam with Noel Phyllis Birkby and Leslie Kanes Weisman (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Core course #4: Professionalism Redefined, Marie I. Kennedy and Joan Forrester Sprague, 19 Aug (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Core course #5: Urban design, Bobbie Sue Hood (Box 11, Folder 12-15)
      - Core course #6: Women and the Built Environment, 13-20 Aug (Box 11, Folder 16-24)
      - Final all-school meeting (Box 11, Folder 25)
      - Ellen, guest speaker and testimony re why came to WSPA, [Digital file available] (Box 12, Folder 26-27)
      - Discussion re Russia, Joan, Margot, Lorna, and Ginny (Box 12, Folder 28-29)
      - "Cake, Fantasy Clip," clips of testimony, [Digital file available] (Box 12, Folder 30)
      - Cake Fantasy film soundtrack (Box 12, Folder 31)
      - sound for slide tape (Box 12, Folder 32)
      - Interview with Susan Morrison, reporter from Biddeford Saco JOURNAL (Box 12, Folder 33)
      - Coordinators' wrap-up? planning for next session? (2 cassettes) (Box 12, Folder 34-35)
    - Second Session (1976), Stevenson College, Santa Cruz, CA
      - Women and the Built Environment (2 cassettes), [Digital file available] (Box 12, Folder 36-37)
    - Third Session (1978), Roger Williams College, Bristol, RI
      - Women and the Built Environment, NPB on single women space (Box 12, Folder 38)
      - Group, Bristol Beach (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - Fourth Session (1979), Regis College, Denver, CO
      - "Veggie City" (Box 12, Folder 40)
      - Hadley Smith (Box 12, Folder 41)
      - H.U.D. women, Joyce Skinner, Mary Anne McKenzie, Kati McDonald, Fern Robertson, Helen Helfner (parts of 2 cassettes), [Digital file available] (Box 12, Folder 42-43)
    - Undated
      - WSPA #6, Brainstorming, Buglisting (Box 12, Folder 44)
      - Children's meeting (Box 12, Folder 45)
      - Jean Baker Miller (Box 12, Folder 46)
      - Core course wrap-up (Box 12, Folder 47)
      - WSPA 3 workshop session, Noel Phyllis Birkby "actualizing environments" (Box 12, Folder 48)
      - Symbolism workshop, Noel Phyllis Birkby and Leslie Kanes Weisman, [Digital file available] (Box 12, Folder 49-50)
      - 18 Aug discussion (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - Slides
    - 1975 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1976 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1977-79 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Photographs
    - 1975 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1976 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1977-78 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Slides
    - 1979 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Negatives, 1975-78 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Films, [See Appendix for descriptions of films]
    - Written material (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - "WSPA" by Lorna McNeur, 1976 (of 1975 session) (Box 14, Folder 1)
      [See box 17A for use copy]
    - "Cake Campus" (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - "WSPA (condensed), reel 1" by Lorna McNeur (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - "WSPA (condensed), reel 2" by Lorna McNeur (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - "Mime"1976 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - "WSPA 2" (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Videotapes
    All original open reel videotapes were sent to VidiPax company for preservation and transfer to Beta Cam and VHS cassette format. The VP number listed after titles are the reel numbers assigned to the original videotapes by VidiPax.
    - Open reel originals, Beta Cam preservation masters, and VHS "Restoration masters" ["Goofed Up Last Nite Tape" {VP# 1} which was not converted to VHS format] (Box 15-17)
      THESE COPIES RETAINED FOR PRESERVATION ONLY. USE COPIES CAN BE MADE FROM THE VHS RESTORATION MASTERS. SEE BOX 17A FOR USE COPIES.
      - 1975
        - "Judy Potter" core course #1 {VP# 6} (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - "Course #2 Tools" {VP# 17} (Box 17, Folder 2)
        - "Katrin's [Adam] class (core course #2), [core course] #4 with Marie, [core course #6] Beginning of Cake Campus" {VP# 15} (Box 17, Folder 3)
        - "Role Playing and tennis, town meeting, course #4" {VP# 16} (Box 17, Folder 4)
        - core course #5 "Sand Models at Beach (#5) Bobbie Sue's [Hood] and Volleyball in Lounge Party" {VP# 3} (Box 17, Folder 5)
        - "WSPA Sandcastle, [core course #5] Bobbie Sue Hood et al--Master Plan St. Francis College, Interviews--meaning of school, Group--lobsters/sex/beer" {VP# 23} (Box 17, Folder 6)
        - Core course #5 "Bobbie Sue Hood--Presentation, St. Francis College" {VP# 4} (Box 17, Folder 7)
        - "#6 core course, Fantasy workshop" {VP# 13} (Box 17, Folder 8)
        - [Core course #6, "Fantasy [workshop] #2, Introduction to Town Meeting" {VP# 24} (Box 17, Folder 9)
        - "Buglisting/Brainstorming #6 course" {VP# 18} (Box 17, Folder 10)
        - "Women's Organizations" {VP# 22} (Box 17, Folder 11)
        - Untitled {VP# 21} (Box 17, Folder 12)
        - "Cake Campus" {VP# 14} (Box 17, Folder 13)
        - "Day Care & WSPA Sign, Cheri Chaney speaking- regional planning, Katrin [Adam] speaking--carpentry tools, Ginny--informal speaking in grass" {VP# 19} (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - 1976
        - Women and the Built Environment: Patti, Cynthia, Phyllis [Birkby], Jane, Mary, Myrna, Ena [Dubnoff], Betsy {VP# 2} (Box 17, Folder 15)
        - Women and the Built Environment: Jolie, Charlotte [Bunch], Carol M., Vicki, Judy, etc. {VP# 5} (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - Viewing copies, films transferred to VHS
        - "WSPA" by Lorna McNeur [transfer of film #1], 1976 (Box 17, Folder 17)
        - "WSPA (condensed), reel 1," by Lorna McNeur, 00h01m00s, [transfer of film #3] (Box 17, Folder 18)
        - "WSPA (condensed), reel 2," by Lorna McNeur, 00h19m40s, [transfer of film #4] (Box 17, Folder 18)
        - "Mime" 00h32m50s, [transfer of film #5], 1976 (Box 17, Folder 18)
        - "WSPA 2," 00h35m22s, [transfer of film #6] (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - Video tapes: written material, 1975 (Box 17)
  - In-house use copies: Videos and films transferred to DVD
    - Video #3: "Katrin's [Adam] class (core course #2), [core course]; #4 with Marie, [core course #6]; Beginning of Cake Campus" 1975 {VP# 15} (Box 17a)
    - Video #8: "WSPA/#6--Fantasy Workshop" {VP#13} (Box 17a)
    - Video #9: "Fantasy2--Intro to Town Meeting" {VP#24} (Box 17a)
    - Video #13: "Cake Campus" {VP# 14} (Box 17a)
    - Video #17: "WSPA" by Lorna McNeur, 1976, [transfer of film #1] (Box 17a)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - SERIES I. GENERAL AND HISTORICAL MATERIALS
    - Memorabilia: t-shirts, 1976, 1978(?), 1979 (Box 18)